<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<vo-dml:model xmlns:vo-dml="http://www.ivoa.net/xml/VODML/v1" 
              xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
              xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ivoa.net/xml/VODML/v1 https://www.ivoa.net/xml/VODML/vo-dml-v1.xsd" 
              vodmlVersion="1.1">	<!-- file generated from VODSL - needs validatate against v1.1 of schema  --> 
      <name>SIA</name>
      <description>
              Implementation of an XML Schema describing a Simple Image
              Access Service.   Based on the Simple Image Access Specification
              by Doug Tody et al.
            </description> 
      <uri/>
      <title>TBD</title>
      <version>1.2</version>
      <lastModified>2023-05-15T11:31:17Z</lastModified>
      <import>
        <name>null</name><!--should not be needed in modern vo-dml -->
        <url>IVOA-v1.0.vo-dml.xml</url>
        <documentationURL>not known</documentationURL>
      </import>
      <import>
        <name>null</name><!--should not be needed in modern vo-dml -->
        <url>VOResource-v1.1.vo-dml.xml</url>
        <documentationURL>not known</documentationURL>
      </import>
            <enumeration>
               <vodml-id>ImageServiceType</vodml-id>
               <name>ImageServiceType</name>
               <description>
                      The class of image service: Cutout, Mosaic, Atlas, Pointed
                        </description>	    
                  <literal>
                    <vodml-id>ImageServiceType.Cutout</vodml-id>
                    <name>Cutout</name>
                    <description>
                             This is a service which extracts or “cuts out” rectangular
                             regions of some larger image, returning an image of the
                             requested size to the client. Such images are usually drawn
                             from a database or a collection of survey images that cover
                             some large portion of the sky. To be considered a cutout
                             service, the returned image should closely approximate (or at
                             least not exceed) the size of the requested region; however,
                             a cutout service will not normally resample (rescale or
                             reproject) the pixel data. A cutout service may mosaic image
                             segments to cover a large region but is still considered a
                             cutout service if it does not resample the data.  Image
                             cutout services are fast and avoid image degredation due to
                             resampling.  
                                   </description>	    
                  </literal>	
                  <literal>
                    <vodml-id>ImageServiceType.Mosaic</vodml-id>
                    <name>Mosaic</name>
                    <description>
                                      This service is similar to the image cutout service
                                      but adds the capability to compute an image of the
                                      size, scale, and projection specified by the
                                      client. Mosaic services include services which
                                      resample and reproject existing image data, as well
                                      as services which generate pixels from some more
                                      fundamental dataset, e.g., a high energy event list
                                      or a radio astronomy measurement set. Image mosaics
                                      can be expensive to generate for large regions but
                                      they make it easier for the client to overlay image
                                      data from different sources. Image mosaicing
                                      services which resample already pixelated data will
                                      degrade the data slightly, unlike the simpler cutout
                                      service which returns the data unchanged.  
                                   </description>	    
                  </literal>	
                  <literal>
                    <vodml-id>ImageServiceType.Atlas</vodml-id>
                    <name>Atlas</name>
                    <description>
                                      This category of service provides access to
                                      pre-computed images that make up a survey of some
                                      large portion of the sky. The service, however, is
                                      not capable of dynamically cutting out requested
                                      regions, and the size of atlas images is
                                      predetermined by the survey. Atlas images may range
                                      in size from small cutouts of extended objects to
                                      large calibrated survey data frames. 
                                   </description>	    
                  </literal>	
                  <literal>
                    <vodml-id>ImageServiceType.Pointed</vodml-id>
                    <name>Pointed</name>
                    <description>
                                      This category of service provides access to
                                      collections of images of many small, “pointed”
                                      regions of the sky. “Pointed” images normally focus
                                      on specific sources in the sky as opposed to being
                                      part of a sky survey. This type of service usually
                                      applies to instrumental archives from observatories
                                      with guest observer programs (e.g., the HST archive)
                                      and other general purpose image archives (e.g., the
                                      ADIL). If a service provides access to both survey
                                      and pointed images, then it should be considered a
                                      Pointed Image Archive for the purposes of this
                                      specification; if a differentiation between the
                                      types of data is desired the pointed and survey data
                                      collections should be registered as separate image
                                      services.  
                                   </description>	    
                  </literal>	
            </enumeration>
            <objectType>
               <vodml-id>SimpleImageAccess</vodml-id>
               <name>SimpleImageAccess</name>
               <description>
                           The capabilities of an SIA implementation.  
                        </description>	    
               <extends>
                  <vodml-ref>VOResource:Capability</vodml-ref>
               </extends>
               <attribute>
                 <vodml-id>SimpleImageAccess.imageServiceType</vodml-id>
                 <name>imageServiceType</name>
                 <description>
                                    The class of image service: Cutout, Mosaic, Atlas, Pointed
                                      </description>	    
                 <datatype>
                    <vodml-ref>SIA:ImageServiceType</vodml-ref>
                 </datatype>
                 <multiplicity>
                   <minOccurs>1</minOccurs>
                   <maxOccurs>1</maxOccurs>
                 </multiplicity>
               </attribute>
               <attribute>
                 <vodml-id>SimpleImageAccess.maxImageSize</vodml-id>
                 <name>maxImageSize</name>
                 <description>
                                          A measure of the largest image the service
                                          can produce given as the maximum number of
                                          pixels along the first or second axes.
                                          Not providing a value indicates that there is 
                                          no effective limit to the size of the images 
                                          that can be returned.  
                                       
                                          This is primarily relevant when the imageServiceType
                                          is “Cutout” or “Mosaic”, indicating the largest 
                                          image that can be created.  When the imageServiceType 
                                          is “Atlas” or “Pointed”, this should be specified only
                                          when there are static images in the archive that can 
                                          be searched for but not returned because they are 
                                          too big.  
                                       
                                          When a service is more fundementally limited
                                          by the total number of pixels in the image, this 
                                          value should be set to the square-root of that
                                          number.  This number will then represent a
                                          lower limit on the maximum length of a side.  
                                      </description>	    
                 <datatype>
                    <vodml-ref>ivoa:integer</vodml-ref>
                 </datatype>
                 <multiplicity>
                   <minOccurs>0</minOccurs>
                   <maxOccurs>1</maxOccurs>
                 </multiplicity>
               </attribute>
               <attribute>
                 <vodml-id>SimpleImageAccess.maxFileSize</vodml-id>
                 <name>maxFileSize</name>
                 <description>
                                         The maximum image file size in bytes.  Not providing 
                                         a value indicates that there is no effective limit 
                                         the size of files that can be returned.  
                                       
                                         This is primarily relevant when the imageServiceType
                                         is “Cutout” or “Mosaic”, indicating the largest 
                                         files that can be created.  When the imageServiceType 
                                         is “Atlas” or “Pointed”, this should be specified only
                                         when there are static images in the archive that can 
                                         be searched for but not returned because they are 
                                         too big.  
                                      </description>	    
                 <datatype>
                    <vodml-ref>ivoa:integer</vodml-ref>
                 </datatype>
                 <multiplicity>
                   <minOccurs>0</minOccurs>
                   <maxOccurs>1</maxOccurs>
                 </multiplicity>
               </attribute>
               <attribute>
                 <vodml-id>SimpleImageAccess.maxRecords</vodml-id>
                 <name>maxRecords</name>
                 <description>
                                         The largest number of records that the Image Query web
                                         method will return. Not providing this value means that
                                         there is no effective limit.  
                                       
                                         This does not refer to the total number of images in 
                                         the archive but rather maximum number of records the 
                                         service is capable of returning.  A limit that is 
                                         greater than the number of images available in the 
                                         archive is equivalent to their being no effective 
                                         limit.  (See RM, Hanisch 2007.)
                                      </description>	    
                 <datatype>
                    <vodml-ref>ivoa:integer</vodml-ref>
                 </datatype>
                 <multiplicity>
                   <minOccurs>0</minOccurs>
                   <maxOccurs>1</maxOccurs>
                 </multiplicity>
               </attribute>
               <composition>
                 <vodml-id>SimpleImageAccess.maxQueryRegionSize</vodml-id>
                 <name>maxQueryRegionSize</name>
                 <description>
                                          The maximum image query region size, expressed in 
                                          decimal degrees.  Not providing this element or 
                                          specifying a value of 360 degrees indicates that 
                                          there is no limit and the entire data collection 
                                          (entire sky) can be queried. 
                                       
                                          Not providing a value is the prefered way to indicate
                                          that there is no limit.
                                      </description>	    
                 <datatype>
                    <vodml-ref>SIA:SkySize</vodml-ref>
                 </datatype>
                 <multiplicity>
                   <minOccurs>0</minOccurs>
                   <maxOccurs>1</maxOccurs>
                 </multiplicity>
               </composition>
               <composition>
                 <vodml-id>SimpleImageAccess.maxImageExtent</vodml-id>
                 <name>maxImageExtent</name>
                 <description>
                                          An upper bound on a region of the sky that can 
                                          be covered by returned images.  That is, no image
                                          returned by this service will cover more than 
                                          this limit.  Not providing this element or 
                                          specifying a value of 360 degrees indicates that 
                                          there is no fundamental limit to the region covered 
                                          by a returned image.  
                                       
                                          When the imageServiceType is “Cutout” or “Mosaic”, 
                                          this represents the largest area that can be requested.
                                          In this case, the “no limit” value means that all-sky
                                          images can be requested.  When the type is “Atlas” or
                                          “Pointed”, it should be a region that most closely 
                                          encloses largest images in the archive, and the ”no
                                          limit” value means that the archive contains all-sky 
                                          (or nearly so) images.  
                                       
                                          Not providing a value is the prefered way to indicate
                                          that there is no limit.
                                      </description>	    
                 <datatype>
                    <vodml-ref>SIA:SkySize</vodml-ref>
                 </datatype>
                 <multiplicity>
                   <minOccurs>0</minOccurs>
                   <maxOccurs>1</maxOccurs>
                 </multiplicity>
               </composition>
               <composition>
                 <vodml-id>SimpleImageAccess.testQuery</vodml-id>
                 <name>testQuery</name>
                 <description>
                                         a set of query parameters that is expected
                                         to produce at least one matched record which
                                         can be used to test the service.  
                                      </description>	    
                 <datatype>
                    <vodml-ref>SIA:Query</vodml-ref>
                 </datatype>
                 <multiplicity>
                   <minOccurs>0</minOccurs>
                   <maxOccurs>1</maxOccurs>
                 </multiplicity>
               </composition>
            </objectType>
            <objectType>
               <vodml-id>SkySize</vodml-id>
               <name>SkySize</name>
               <description></description>	    
               <attribute>
                 <vodml-id>SkySize.long</vodml-id>
                 <name>long</name>
                 <description>
                                  The maximum size in the longitude (R.A.) direction
                                  given in degrees
                               </description>	    
                 <datatype>
                    <vodml-ref>ivoa:real</vodml-ref>
                 </datatype>
                 <multiplicity>
                   <minOccurs>1</minOccurs>
                   <maxOccurs>1</maxOccurs>
                 </multiplicity>
               </attribute>
               <attribute>
                 <vodml-id>SkySize.lat</vodml-id>
                 <name>lat</name>
                 <description>
                                  The maximum size in the latitude (Dec.) direction 
                                  given in degrees
                               </description>	    
                 <datatype>
                    <vodml-ref>ivoa:real</vodml-ref>
                 </datatype>
                 <multiplicity>
                   <minOccurs>1</minOccurs>
                   <maxOccurs>1</maxOccurs>
                 </multiplicity>
               </attribute>
            </objectType>
            <objectType>
               <vodml-id>SkyPos</vodml-id>
               <name>SkyPos</name>
               <description></description>	    
               <attribute>
                 <vodml-id>SkyPos.long</vodml-id>
                 <name>long</name>
                 <description>
                                  The sky position in the longitude (R.A.) direction 
                               </description>	    
                 <datatype>
                    <vodml-ref>ivoa:real</vodml-ref>
                 </datatype>
                 <multiplicity>
                   <minOccurs>1</minOccurs>
                   <maxOccurs>1</maxOccurs>
                 </multiplicity>
               </attribute>
               <attribute>
                 <vodml-id>SkyPos.lat</vodml-id>
                 <name>lat</name>
                 <description>
                                  The sky position in the latitude (Dec.) direction 
                               </description>	    
                 <datatype>
                    <vodml-ref>ivoa:real</vodml-ref>
                 </datatype>
                 <multiplicity>
                   <minOccurs>1</minOccurs>
                   <maxOccurs>1</maxOccurs>
                 </multiplicity>
               </attribute>
            </objectType>
            <objectType>
               <vodml-id>Query</vodml-id>
               <name>Query</name>
               <description>
                           A query to be sent to the service
                        </description>	    
               <attribute>
                 <vodml-id>Query.verb</vodml-id>
                 <name>verb</name>
                 <description>
                                    the verbosity level to use where 0 means the bare
                                    minimum set of columns and 3 means the full set of 
                                    available columns.
                                </description>	    
                 <datatype>
                    <vodml-ref>ivoa:integer</vodml-ref>
                 </datatype>
                 <multiplicity>
                   <minOccurs>0</minOccurs>
                   <maxOccurs>1</maxOccurs>
                 </multiplicity>
               </attribute>
               <attribute>
                 <vodml-id>Query.extras</vodml-id>
                 <name>extras</name>
                 <description>
                                    any extra (particularly non-standard) parameters that must 
                                    be provided (apart from what is part of base URL given by 
                                    the accessURL element).
                                 
                                    this value should be in the form of name=value
                                    pairs delimited with ampersands.  
                                </description>	    
                 <datatype>
                    <vodml-ref>ivoa:string</vodml-ref>
                 </datatype>
                 <multiplicity>
                   <minOccurs>0</minOccurs>
                   <maxOccurs>1</maxOccurs>
                 </multiplicity>
               </attribute>
               <composition>
                 <vodml-id>Query.pos</vodml-id>
                 <name>pos</name>
                 <description>
                                    the center position of the rectangular region that 
                                    should be used as part of the query to the SIA service. 
                                </description>	    
                 <datatype>
                    <vodml-ref>SIA:SkyPos</vodml-ref>
                 </datatype>
                 <multiplicity>
                   <minOccurs>0</minOccurs>
                   <maxOccurs>1</maxOccurs>
                 </multiplicity>
               </composition>
               <composition>
                 <vodml-id>Query.size</vodml-id>
                 <name>size</name>
                 <description>
                                    the rectangular size of the region that should be 
                                    used as part of the query to the SIA service.
                                </description>	    
                 <datatype>
                    <vodml-ref>SIA:SkySize</vodml-ref>
                 </datatype>
                 <multiplicity>
                   <minOccurs>0</minOccurs>
                   <maxOccurs>1</maxOccurs>
                 </multiplicity>
               </composition>
            </objectType>
</vo-dml:model>
